Linda Troeller Papers
Linda Troeller Papers
1949-2016
Troeller, Linda
10.25 linear ft.
American photographer. Collection includes published material, memorabilia, original photographs and photographic prints.
4658896
Biographical History
Linda Troeller (1949- ) is an award-winning American art photographer known for her investigations into women and sexuality, self-portraiture, AIDS/HIV, and water and healing.
Born to Marion and Raymond Troeller in New Jersey, she was popular in high school (a cheerleader, queen of three proms, and Miss Ocean County Fair), and excelled at creative writing. She discovered photography while a work-study student at Ghost Ranch visiting Georgia O'Keeffe, who encouraged her.
Troeller graduated from Reed College of Media in West Virginia with a BS in journalism in 1971, and received her MS in photojournalism and public relations from Syracuse University's Newhouse School of Communication a year later. She spent a year as an assistant at the Ansel Adams Workshops in Yosemite (1974), and received her MFA from Syracuse University in 1975. Her teaching career includes positions as professor of photography at Indiana University and Stockton University, visiting lecturer at Yale University, and adjunct professor at Parsons School of Design, among others. She has published several books of her photographs, alone and in collaboration, including Healing Waters, The Erotic Lives of Women, and Living in the Chelsea Hotel, about her twelve years of residence in New York City's iconic home of artists, writers, actors, and musicians.
She has been recognized many times for her work, including several Lucie Awards, a Women of Achievement Award from Douglass College, and an award from the New York Foundation of the Arts. Her work is in the permanent collections at the Museum of Fine Arts in Houston, University of Texas at Austin, and galleries in Medellin, Colombia.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Linda Troeller Papers consists of memorabilia, photographs, published material, and works by Troeller, and spans her entire career as photographer and artist.
Biographical material contains a c.v. and short and long autobiographical sketches.
Memorabilia consists of a "journal book" presented to Troeller after teaching at the Salzburg Summer Art Institute, and a number of three-ring binders compiled by Troeller and reflecting various stages in her life. The binders contain a wide range of matrial, including letters, photographs, cards, high school and college items, clippings, articles, family-related material, and more.
Prints contains original photographic prints by Troeller in various sizes. Most are of photographs that appeared in published works included in the collection ( Healing Waters, Spa), but some are standalone projects (Foto Chicas of Medellin). There are also photographs documenting the aftermath of a house fire that destroyed her home.
Published material contains books, magazines, documentaries and other published material containing Troeller's work, or about Troeller and her work. There is also a 43-minute documentary on Troeller by Jeff McKay, with accompanying publicity.
Works by Troeller contains published and unpublished items created or authored by Troeller, or as collaborative efforts between Troeller and others (for example, the book Spa Journeys with photographs by Linda Troeller and text by Annette Foglino). Of particular interest here are "A Decade in Photography 1970-1980," a bound volume of Troeller's diary notes, photos and journal entries with extensive handwritten annotations and corrections; and "Peter," a handmade artist's book created by Troeller for a college photography course.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is alphabetical by type, title or topic.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of noted photographers, both manuscript collections and cataloged in our Rare Books collection. Please refer to to located additional manuscript collections, and to to located cataloged items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Photography; Women Authors; McKay, Jeff.; Troeller, Linda.; Chelsea Hotel -- Pictorial works.; The erotic lives of women.; Healing waters.; Orgasm: photographs and interviews.; Email love.; AIDS (Disease) -- Pictorial works.; Fire in art.; Hot springs -- Pictorial works.; Hydrotherapy -- Pictorial works.; Photography, Artistic.; Photojournalism.; Women -- Colombia -- Pictorial works.; Women -- Sexual behavior -- Interviews.; Women -- Sexual behavior -- Pictorial works.; Women photographers.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Books.; Born digital.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; DVDs.; Photographic prints.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Self-portraits.; Photographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Linda Troeller, 2015.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical sketch, c.v. (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  Titles and descriptions of all Ringbinder Notebooks are verbatim, as given by the donor. More detailed descriptions of each ringbinder, also provided by donor, are in each box.
  - Erotic Lives of Women exhibit posters, 1998; 2010; 2 items (Oversize 6)
  - Journal book presented to Linda after teaching at the Salzburg Summar Art Academy, thank-you letters, photographs, notes, etc. (Box 1)
  - Ringbinder Notebook #1: "Women in Photography" Class taught at Syracuse University (Oversize 1)
  - Ringbinder Notebook #2: Linda MFA study at SU on to the Teaching Years (Oversize 1)
  - Ringbinder Notebook #3: Linda - Baby to University (Oversize 1)
  - Ringbinder Notebook #4: Correspondence with David Broda, a MS Newhouse SU graduate with me on SU program in Munich with Professor Richards (Oversize 2)
  - Ringbinder Notebook #5: The TB-AIDS DIARY (Oversize 2)
    See also Published material: TB-SIDA Diary above.
  - Ringbinder Notebook #6: Coverage of books, Healing Waters, Aperture, and The Erotic Lives of Women, Scalo 1998 and Chelsea Hotel, Blurb and my Curating show for 125th Anniversary and Pop UP Eviction Event (Oversize 2)
  - Ringbinder Notebook #7: Photo-Related Letters, correspondents include Ansel Adams, Richard Rogers, John W. Hill, Gordon Lish, Linda Connor, Peter Galassi, Lucien Clergue, Shelby Lee Adams, Eikoh Hosoe (Oversize 3)
  - Ringbinder Notebook #8: Emeritus Professor Lawrence Jasud Letters on Photography Letters to me about photography and life (Oversize 3)
  - Ringbinder Notebook #9: TREASURED DOCUMENTS JFK signed letter etc., correspondents include John F. Kennedy, Jr., Troeller's mother and husband, and former boyfriends (Oversize 3)
- Prints
  - Chelsea Hotel, 1995; 1999-2000,; 2002,; 2006-2007; 8 items (Oversize 6)
  - Healing Waters and Spa, 1992; 1994,; 1996,; undated; 13 items (Oversize 6)
  - Foto Chicas of Medellin, 2010; 7 items (Oversize 5)
  - Orgasm, 2014; 8 items (Oversize 6)
  - Photographs from the Ashes, 2016; includes a lengthy artist's statement about the fire that gutted her house, the aftermath of which is documented in the photographs, and an itemized list; 115 items (Oversize 7)
  - Photographs from the Ashes, digital files, 2016; troeller_003; 4GB sim card containing digital images; not reviewed; 1 item (Oversize 7)
  - Portraits / Lothar Troeller, 2000-2005; excerpts from Email Love artist book; 5 items (Oversize 6)
  - Self-Portraits / Portraits / Preface by Tony Kamps, Curator, 1973-1976; 2003; 8 items (Oversize 6)
  - Self-Portraits on Color Polaroid, 1981; 1989; 5 items (Oversize 5)
  - TB-AIDS Diary Color Cibachrome Prints, 1988-1989; 17 items (Oversize 5)
- Published material
  - Die 100 Jahreszeiten der Toskana des Ostens (Mitteldeutscher Verlag), 2003; photographs by Linda Troeller, text by Micky Remann; in German; signed by Troeller (Oversize 4)
  - Aperture spring catalog, 1998; cover: Waterbalancing (Box 1)
  - Apolda fashion catalogs, 1999; 2002,; 2005; for Apolda, Germany museum; includes published catalogs as well as sheets of contact prints; 3 volumes (Oversize 4)
  - CAST award catalog, 1975; next-to-last page: Women in Greenhouses (Box 1)
  - Combinations, vol. 1 no. 1, 1977; p. 21: Homage to Tina Modotti (Box 1)
  - Diário TB-SIDA, Hospital of Coimbra, Portugal, 1970-1980; includes typed notes from talk entitled "TB-AIDS diary: Stigma Bearing Roses" and small published book entitled Infected With, along with two spiral-bound volumes of newspaper and magazine articles and clippings about the project; 3 folders (Box 1)
    See also Ringbinder Notebook #5: The TB-AIDS DIARY.
  - Erotic Lives of Women clippings, 1998; articles, reviews, excerpts, etc. (Box 1)
    See also Works by Troeller: The Erotic Lives of Women for the book itself.
  - Heresies #12: Sex Issue, 1975; p.87: Leg over Cactus, Bridal Rite (Box 1)
  - Inside the Frame, 2015; troeller_001, troeller_002; documentary film by Jeff McKay about Troeller and her work; color, 43 min.; includes clipping of article, flier from New Jersey International Film Festival, etc.; 2 DVDs (Box 2)
  - LIFE magazine, Sep 1995; p. 45: Jacuzzi, Calistoga Hot Springs, CA (Box 2)
  - L'Oeil en Seyne, 1994; pp. 52-53: L'eau; catalog from invitational exhibit in Paris (Box 2)
  - Mucalinda: Self-Portraits and Self-Reflections (Elizabeth Avedon), 2011; photographs and text by Troeller, with additional text by by Toby Kamp and Kalie Brooks; part of a 50 book artist series (Box 2)
  - Self-Portrayal, Friends of Photography, 1977; Snowbird (self-portrait) (Box 2)
  - Where Do We Go From Here? (F-Stop Fotofestival), 2009; pp. 174-174: four photographs from Chelsea Hotel (Box 2)
  - Women by Women: Erotische Fotografie (Prestel), 2003; plate 105: Yoko, from Erotic Lives of Women; includes small postcard from the opening in Berlin (Box 2)
- Works by Troeller
  - A Decade in Photography, 1970-1980; diary notes, photos, journal entries; bound typescript pages with annotations and corrections; softcover (Box 2)
  - Email Love, 2007; self-published collection of Troeller's photographs, with emails between her and her husband Lothar; hardcover with jacket (Box 3)
  - Erotic Lives of Women (Scalo), 1998; book of Troeller's photographs with interviews by Marion Schneider (Box 3)
    See also Published material: Erotic Lives of Women clippings.
  - Healing Waters (Aperture), 1998; book of Troeller's photographs, preface by Dr. Wolfgang Becker, introduction by Dr. Yves Treguer, signed by Troeller (Box 3)
  - Hotel Chelsea Atmosphere: An Artist's Memoir, 2006; self-published collection of Troeller's photographs, accompanied by "Dear Chelsea Hotel" letters from long-time residents; hardcover with jacket (Box 3)
  - Living in the Chelsea Hotel (Schiffer), 2015; photographic collage of 76 images and vignettes; cover mockup only (Box 3)
  - Orgasm (Daylight), 2014; book of Troeller's photographs with interviews by Marion Schneider; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Peter, 1970; handmade artist book; noted as "for Professor Jerry Ash's Photo 101 course" (Oversize 4)
  - A Photographer's Tale, 2005; draft dummy for self-published autobiography; softcover (Box 3)
  - Sex and Transcendence, 2005; self-published autobiography, never published; hardcover with jacket (Box 3)
  - Spa Journeys (powerHouse books), 2004; photographs by Linda Troeller, text by Annette Foglino (Box 3)